This is Wyatt, and on today's episode, I was joined by Andrew McKenzie, founder of Agant.
Agant is building a GBP stablecoin with aspirations to branch into other adjacent products.
I hope you enjoy our conversation.
This is an expression of their personal opinion.
This podcast is for informational purposes only.
Brought down by bad mortgage investments, Lehman, which has 25,000 employees, will be liquidated.
The federal government loans American International Group, AIG, $85 billion.
This is a different kind of market, and the Fed is asleep.
The federal government is stepping in to stabilize Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac, the two mortgage
giants that have been threatened by the housing crisis.
The Bank of England has pumped 75 billion pounds more into Britain's ailing economy
with a new round of quantitative easing.
We print a couple trillion dollars and all of a sudden people start to worry.
So out of this worry, we have something called the Bitcoin, Bitcoin.
Andy, founder of Agant, thanks for joining us today.
Pleasure to be here.
Thanks for having me.
I have to check.
You might be our first Scottish guest we've ever had on the brink.
Maybe.
I know Nick obviously spent some time up in Scotland, so I guess he can reclaim a little
bit of time up here.
But yeah, I just need to remember to speak slowly and clearly as my mom always tells
me.
Yeah, exactly.
Partial credit, maybe.
Are you a Liverpool fan?
I try to stay impartial, so my dad and I, we support League United.
Nice.
So a good season there, too.
Exactly.
Would love a personal background.
Tell us who you are, why you're here.
Would love to hear about how you're involved in the crypto space.
I guess my background is maybe not quite the same as a lot of founders in this space.
I'm from an agricultural background.
I grew up in the country just north of Edinburgh.
I spent most of my childhood in and around farming, ended up studying business and agriculture
at university and then kind of just fell into my first job, which was working for a large
veg company up in Scotland, a grower, manufacturer and distributor, and worked on the OTC desk
for them, buying and selling carrots and other soft vegetables like broccoli and Brussels
sprouts, you know, importing and exporting them in and out of the UK.
So maybe a little bit of an unconventional trading start to a career, but certainly one
that I really enjoyed.
It really opens your eyes up to what drives markets.
Do those trade on an exchange or over the phone or how's that happening?
Purely over the phone.
A lot of wheeling and dealing, so to speak.
There's a few markets that you can arbitrage quite nicely.
So yeah, it's just a really interesting start to my sort of finance career, so to speak,
in terms of what drives markets and what fuels the price action that we used to see.
I didn't really get into blockchain, digital assets, crypto, whatever we call it these
days until 2020 when the price of Bitcoin and Ethereum disintegrated.
My interest spiked and then got hugely into DeFi in 2021.
Worked for a firm that unfortunately became a victim of FTX saga.
So came out of the space and ended up going back into traditional finance and worked for
a firm moving funds cross-border for agricultural businesses.
So worked in the payment space for them, helping them manage the risk and also remit
funds.
And I guess very quickly realized that there's a really effective and efficient way of moving
value and that is this thing called the blockchain.
And that's really what sort of fueled the start of what is now Agan.
What prompted Agan and what is it today?
Agan is primarily a UK domiciled stablecoin issuance and infrastructure provider.
We kicked things off 40 months ago now in January of last year.
I guess it kind of was a combination of reasons.
So the UK as a financial center globally stands out.
British pounds sterling is the fourth largest currency in circulation and the fourth most
traded UK financial services in London and also across the UK have a global presence.
But there are no pounds sterling on chain, there's no GBP on chain.
And so I always felt like there was a need and it was an obvious thing to do.
And then in November of 2023, when I was still working in payments for ag businesses, like
I said, there was a much more efficient and effective way of remitting these funds.
And then I guess what came in at that time was Bank of England and the FCA published
the discussion papers into the use of stablecoins in both retail and systemic payment systems
in the UK.
I guess for me that was sort of the first catalyst to sort of starting what is now Agan.
The regulators were ready to have the conversation.
A lot of my experience in digital assets and in crypto, you know, weren't maybe the best.
I was subject to a lot of grifts and stuff like that.
I guess everyone kind of was in defi.
And so I really wanted to try and create something that was doing things the right way when it
comes to compliance and the way in which the business governs itself and its ethos.
That's really what we set off on.
So I was involved in a couple of side projects with some friends and we were on call some
lawyers and I just pitched the question to them and said, what's your views on our UK
I made on myself, UK regulated, privately issued stablecoin.
GBP stablecoin, to be clear.
GBP stablecoin, you know, we really tried to set out in creating what we kind of call
the most boring kind of stablecoin because we feel if there's going to be a successful
UK GBP ecosystem on chain, we need to have this foundation layer that doesn't do very
much that everyone can trust that is, you know, transparent, secure and untrusted.
What's the current state of USD stablecoin adoption in the UK?
It's quite high.
We don't really have any other choice.
The figures aren't the most accurate at the moment, but somewhere between five and seven
million people own crypto in the UK.
And most of them hold, it varies depending on what their total holding value is, but
most of them hold somewhere between nine and 25% of those funds in staples.
So virtually all of them are in USD at present.
And from your perspective, today there being no alternative, you guys are attempting to
build the GBP stablecoin.
Are they owning USD because they're trapped into doing so or by choice?
I think it's a combination of things.
We've always used the crypto ecosystem as dollars, and I don't really think that that's
actually going to change in the short to medium term.
That's where most of the liquidity is, and it's where most of the liquidity will continue
to be particularly in DeFi.
Where we've made a differentiation, and it's quite pedantic, but we very much view ourselves
as a fintech that integrates and utilizes blockchain technology as opposed to a crypto business.
That's where we see the real value in non-US dollar stablecoins.
It's not necessarily directly providing liquidity against the majors.
I guess that might be a part of our business and other UK GBP issuers' businesses as well.
However, attacking the wider UK financial services ecosystem, helping to solve a few
use cases or problems for those organizations is where we see the real growth in our proposition.
And those problems you're mentioning, are those highlighted by the rise of crypto and
adoption elsewhere?
Are the UK financial institutions going to have problems because of crypto adoption,
or is it traditional legacy problems unrelated to crypto that you guys are looking to solve?
I think it's a combination of things.
I think we've put up with a number of underlying problems for quite a period of time because
as far as the industry was concerned, there wasn't really a particularly suitable alternative
that had the network effects that, for example, crypto has.
A lot of firms got very good at putting plasters on old infrastructure and tying it together
with credit lines.
They've found ways around the settlement delays, et cetera, but that's reflected in the counterparty
risk that they might need to carry or the amount of regulatory capital that they need
to hold to offset those issues.
I guess to tie it back, Nick VanEck always says that if you look at fintech for the last
15, 20 years, the front end of the UI, the UX, all of that has seen massive innovation
whereas the back end hasn't, whereas what we feel that both crypto, blockchain technology
and stable coins present is that back end infrastructure layer coming up to match the
front end that we currently have.
We've built this multi-layer convoluted system and the hope is that you'll be able to settle
collateral instantly, especially when you're doing this cross currency.
I can't wait till FX hopefully moves on chain.
What kind of inbound are you guys getting?
Who's interested to use this product?
This time last year, we felt like we needed to be a retail focused organization.
We always felt like the institutions weren't necessarily going to be ready.
I remember going to the Digital Asset Summit in London in March last year and I think the
theme at that point was the institutions are coming and that's kind of what we felt.
A summer of last year, we kind of turned that on its head and it was probably thanks to
a couple of the advisors that we brought in and they said, you know, really the institutions
are ready and being institutional first is really the avenue that you should pursue.
Originally our focus is very much within sort of the crypto industry, so to speak, in terms
of what we were trying to speak to exchanges and market makers and OTC desk, everyone that
had direct exposure to crypto.
And then in the autumn of last year, a couple of asset managers started to poke their head
up and that's where things really started to get interesting because we kind of knew
that they were sort of dabbling, but we didn't necessarily know how progressed they were
in their own ideology and thinking in terms of what they want to do for their own organizations,
but also how ready they were to start those conversations.
So now I would almost say there's been more that's happened since the start of the year
than happened in all of last year.
Now, you know, our conversations are across, you know, banks, hedge funds, asset managers,
payment service providers, electronic money institutions.
There's a whole spread at that point, this time last year, we felt that stable coins
were really trying to solve problems within crypto, facing off against digital assets
or like you say, maybe on the FX piece, because we kind of just viewed traditional financial
payment systems, particularly domestic ones and internal to the UK especially as being
solved.
But what's become really apparent is if I was to send money via faster payments, for
example, to you in the UK, you know, it's free for me to do that.
If you're the infrastructure provider behind that, if you're the institution that's providing
that service, it's definitely not free.
And so there's a real opportunity as a stable coin issuer where you can turn something that
is currently a cost to that business into something that is a net contributor, you know,
a revenue generator to that business.
We're seeing a lot of interest, particularly in the inner and around that side, how businesses
are able to become a lot more competitive in some of the product offerings that they
currently aren't able to really compete on.
And I imagine if you're a centralized exchange in the US, you deal with USD stablecoins operationally
and then users are off ramping into USD accounts.
That's relatively simple.
But if you're a UK exchange today and users are holding deposits on the exchange at USD
stables and you have to manage that off ramp function and vice versa to GBP, either the
exchange or an on ramp off ramp provider is taking FX risk because you don't have that
instant crypto to crypto settlement.
So I imagine you guys could really be effective in that flow.
We see a lot of streamlining on the on ramp in particular.
At the moment, it's kind of a patchwork in terms of how you on ramp into US dollar stables.
And like you say, you have that FX that either you as the user take on if you're holding
dollars in your wallet, whether that's in a centralized exchange or in your self-custodial
wallet, which isn't great.
I at a point earned in USDC, I had to take on that FX risk.
Luckily for me, there was a bit of political turmoil in the UK, so the FX was going in
my favor.
But for example, you know, if you are a large financial institution, a few basis points
here or there can really make quite a big difference to you.
For them, it's a little bit cumbersome having to hedge out that risk.
So being able to offer them if they denominate themselves in British pounds, being able to
be on chain in British pounds makes a lot of sense as well.
Do you think you see local currency stablecoins pop up around the world in the next few months,
couple of years?
Yeah.
We are starting to see that in a lot of the conversations that we are having, and we're
looking at how we can simplify the flows that currently exist.
For example, we're talking to a group of guys in Singapore, they're doing some exciting
stuff out there.
And we were actually talking through those flows, you know, if they were to send us Singapore
dollars at the moment, the number of intermediaries that we'd each need to go through.
And we think that by taking it on chain, we can reduce that from a roughly five intermediaries
to three.
So that's quite cool.
And that's quite exciting.
Obviously, that's going to take time to build up and to get that organic liquidity in there.
But it's moving in the right direction.
People are starting to innovate in those sort of areas.
And particularly between like the UK and India, the UK and Global South, you know, the UK
and Africa, Nigeria, Kenya, South Africa, there's a lot of flow that goes that way.
And so being able to do that on chain and like you say, you know, being able to settle
into stable coins in those jurisdictions and not necessarily have to do the off ramp simplifies
the process drastically.
How do regulators view crypto and a GBP stablecoin, as well as larger banks, institutions that
might have regulatory influence?
Stablecoins in the UK, to go back a step, are kind of split, if that makes sense.
And we have two regulators, we have the FCA, which basically regulates all financial institutions
and then we have the PRA, which sits under the Bank of England, which is the UK Central
Bank, which regulates banks.
And so they are going down different regulatory paths and they're starting to come together
and they're starting to talk a little bit more and the understanding between the regulators
and firms and institutions in the sector is starting to align.
However, there's still quite a long way to go.
The UK is behind other jurisdictions in terms of where it is in its regulatory process,
we're still at the discussion paper stage, the DPs and the SIs are still coming out
and we're still talking about a lot of things.
However, I do feel like there's a lot more clarity in how stablecoins are going to be
viewed.
You know, the FCA, for example, we're going to look at them as a crypto asset and not
as e-money and making those differentiations has been really important for not only us
as an organisation, but also a lot of the businesses that we want to face off because
really at the end of the day, they can have as much innovation and be as excited about
stablecoins as they like, but if their compliance and legal departments aren't willing to sign
off, then it's not going to go very far.
I guess to sum it up, we don't have any regulation at the moment.
We're trying to fit stablecoins into existing registrations that currently exist and I think
that'll be about a year or two away before we get any dedicated UK stablecoin regulations.
So I guess at the moment we can backdoor through anti-money laundering registrations.
So to speak, but I would say there is a little bit of hostility still there, but there's
been a huge shift in the tone, which is what is really positive.
A couple of our advisors were at some roundtables at Point Zero last week and there was a lot
of central bankers there and again, they said the tone of the conversation and the level
of understanding is quite exciting and making them feel quite optimistic.
There's definitely a shift to being pro-innovation, crypto-friendly and trying to be one of the
first movers within this as we go forward.
You must have some interesting conversations with powerful institutions because I imagine
you speak to banks about all the things you guys want to do and are excited to do and
you're probably in some ways worried.
What if they decide they want to issue a GBP stablecoin?
Does that cross your mind?
It's a question that comes up almost every day.
Someone says, what if the large incumbents come in?
You can almost split that conversation up into a number of different buckets, so to
speak.
If you look at banks at the moment, there's a real worry from the PRA, which is under
the Bank of England, the Financial Regulatory Authority, that regulated businesses could
start offering unregulated financial products.
They're really saying to banks, we need you to wait until we have the clarity that we
need until we have the regulation before we can have you start doing this.
It's not as though that the banks don't want to, it's that they can.
We've been making the most of that, but then if you look at existing stablecoin businesses
and organizations, I think a lot of them, with the conversations that we've had, they
feel like there's still so much for them to go after doing what they're doing at the moment
within the dollar economy itself.
There's still so much growth, so we're operating under the radar.
I think there's a lot more traction within the UK and within GBP within the last three,
four months than there was even last year.
The tide is really starting to turn.
Will they allow this innovation to exist, the British regulatory bodies?
I would say the folks are probably lobbying there, or do you think there will be pushback?
I don't think there'll be pushback from the banks.
I don't think there'll be pushback from the industry itself.
I mean, UK financial institutions have always been quite open to innovation.
That's refreshing.
I wish we had that.
Yeah.
Maybe that's a slightly controversial view.
I'm not sure.
But if you look at, for example, payments innovation in the UK, we were very quick to
move to mobile banking, for example.
We were one of the first countries to start using contactless with the widespread adoption
that we had.
So people are quite open to using new forms of money and new forms of payment systems.
So I think financial institutions especially can see the advantages.
I think a lot of them were going to do it earlier in 2022.
I know there was a large UK bank that was looking at doing their own stablecoin and
actually offering cryptocurrency purchases within their own online banking app.
But then FTX happened and the compliance department just said, hell no, we can't do any of this
ourselves.
So it's not that they don't want to do it, it's that they can't at the moment.
How important is it that you guys are a UK based company?
I think it's one of the most important parts for us at the moment, getting a local regulator
on site, you need to have a local presence, as particularly with the FCA authorizations
are globally recognized as one of the most trusted and respected regulators globally.
It gives us a few benefits, it enables us to conduct a few more activities, some of
which require local authorizations to do those activities.
But typically the regulator likes to use local authorization as a condition for being able
to undertake certain types of business, particularly when it comes to facing off retail customers.
And not only that, it gives UK institutions a lot of confidence.
The city is one of these strange places where if you come knocking on their door and you're
regulated through one of the slightly more grayer jurisdictions, their tails are automatically
going to be up and they're going to be saying, hang on, why we tried to circumvent what's
already there.
It gives us the ability to get partnerships, particularly with compliance teams.
Yeah, I imagine there's a comfort level that comes with it.
I'm curious for your perspective, being a stablecoin issuer that is the traditional
business of net interest margin.
You make money on deposits, especially in the context in the UK.
You've had innovation in the fintech space.
You've seen new players in mobile banking.
You've seen new business models.
How do you look at your best viable business model long term or even more widely?
What the best business model for someone taking on this opportunity of new currency stablecoin?
The net interest margin is always going to be a factor.
I think what's lucky for us at the moment is that the FCA has said that no interest
shall be given to the token holder.
They don't want yield bearing stablecoins to be a thing.
Interesting.
They proactively said that.
Yeah.
They all kind of at the moment want one to always be one.
However, I think as our business develops and changes and grows, we don't want to necessarily
just be relying on that because you're basically one line within a piece of regulation away
from your entire business model no longer existing.
We see a lot on the transaction fee side.
We actually see a lot on the banking element as well.
If you're able to access deposited funds, you can potentially offer banking services
to corporates like lending payments, but then also on the yield bearing side as well.
We see a lot of opportunity there.
I think regulators are more open to a new bank than an organization like us progressing
that looks very like a bank as opposed to an existing bank starting to offer new forms
of business.
You know, they're a little bit cagey about the contagion risk that sits there.
So UK banks have real uphill battle with regulators and that's something that I think we as an
organization can capture within our own business model.
So I think over time, we would quite like a Gantt to start looking more like a bank
and the types of banking services that we'd be able to offer, we can generate revenue
from that.
With regulatory considerations in mind, how do you look at launching on private blockchains
versus permissionless blockchains?
I think they all have their place and we've talked to some asset managers that want to
solve, you know, use stablecoins to solve an internal use case.
And so whether that's on a public ledger or private ledger is kind of neither here nor
there.
However, I am a strong believer that we should be on public blockchains as much as we can.
And I think when you see a lot of the innovations in being able to, you know, hide transactions
and shield vulnerabilities away, we want a degree of transparency, but there are times
and places where that transparency isn't good.
There's certain networks out there that are really innovating in that space and making
it quite exciting for us to be a part of that.
And going to institutions, we can see the value proposition of both.
That's a personal viewpoint, to be clear, the preference for permissionless blockchains.
No, that is a personal preference.
I mean, I think there's a lot of advantages to public permissionless technology.
What other product directions are you excited about, potential adjacencies?
We get really excited about being able to generate sustainable risk-adjusted returns.
And I know that sounds quite a mouthful, but I feel like a lot of the returns in DeFi aren't
particularly sustainable long term.
I think being able to bring real world returns and distribute them on chain, you know, things
get quite exciting.
It's quite apparent that if you're going to take financial services on chain, the risk
free rate isn't necessarily attractive enough.
And so you need to be offering something that is slightly more enhanced, a few percent more.
So being able to do that is something that we get quite excited about.
But then there's different aspects, you know, I was having a conversation earlier today
about, you know, effectively creating, you know, funds of funds where, you know, you
can diversify that risk.
So, yeah, risk weighted returns on chain where people can see, you know, enhanced returns
without necessarily having to take on incredible amounts of risk.
I personally get quite excited about that side of things.
Yeah, it's interesting because I feel like we've built two opposite sides of the coin
in that you have savings accounts, almost traditional bank accounts, which allow you
to hold money very well.
And then you have the highly speculative DeFi yield side.
But the middle ground is not that well served.
You've Goldman Sachs high yield savings accounts and some equivalents, but it still feels like,
to your point, attractive, steady rate investment products are somewhat gate kept.
100% and a lot of these organizations and funds that maybe offer these financial products,
like you say, you know, the minimum ticket might be 10 million pounds.
We were able to come in and we were able to act as the LP for those organizations and
then we can effectively fractionalize our stake within them.
And we're effectively democratizing those returns because in reality, if you're able
to take, let's say, you know, somewhere between 8 and 12% annually, the returns are completely
uncorrelated to financial markets and the level of risk that you're taking is significantly
lower than that within, you know, traditional financial markets.
And that's quite an attractive proposition for a lot of people in a lot of organizations.
If you look at USD stablecoins and how they eventually came to what I'd consider now
rapidly growing adoption, there was a pretty slow bleed for a while.
You had them come into existence and it took a while to get to 10 million, 20 million in total supply.
Do you think that will be the same process we see with a GBP stablecoin and other alternatives?
And then we'll have an inflection and that's for rapid growth we see with USD today?
Not really.
When we launch hopefully in the next few months, I don't think our growth will be by any means linear.
But I don't think it will be slow initially because I do think there is a base level demand
that really wants a financial product on chain that isn't necessarily dollars.
I think initially for us to get to, you know, a circle or a teller kind of size, then yeah,
you know, that's going to take a while and there probably will need to be an inflection point that
we would consider as reaching mass adoption.
However, for us to get to a modest size with a few commas and zeros,
I honestly don't believe that that's going to be particularly long for us.
You know, the types of conversations that we're having and the types of organizations
that are reaching out to us demonstrates that there is this demand.
You know, I think that's one thing that has been quite surprising
is how easily we've been able to have a lot of the conversations that we're currently having.
What Dollar Stablecoins has done for us is they demonstrate the proof isn't pudding.
What's also quite helpful for us is that global financial markets,
while the majority is dollars, there's a lot of value that's also not.
The UK financial ecosystem, you know, the whole industry, a lot of that's not dollars,
but a lot of the use cases can be applied directly to those organizations.
We're feeling pretty optimistic about our trajectory and also that for the industry as a whole.
To your point, I think there is and will continue to be demand.
Who do you think are the winners and losers
once you guys are at scale and other comparable players are at scale?
I sat on a panel a few weeks ago in front of a bunch of bankers and I basically said, you know,
you need to start embracing this or you're going to become a victim of it.
I would say if I was any financial institution, you know, the investment banks are the investment
banks. On the whole, if they manage their risk, they're going to survive in one firm or another.
Where I would be nervous is if I was within the retail banking system.
If I'm an individual within the UK, for example, and I have my savings with a standard high street
retail bank, I'm only covered up to £85,000. Anything more than that, I'm subject to the
bank's own risks and its own reserves. They're fractionally backed. And if I could be fully
backed, I would choose to be fully backed, not fractionally backed. So yeah, I think the UK
retail banking system is probably the most at risk, although I'm sure the regulator will find
ways to protect them if they need to. Presumably these yield-bearing,
inter-spring products will be interesting for them though, at least as business models that they can
almost leach onto. I think so. And I think maybe that's what we start to do is view them as a
distribution channel, look at how we can integrate. I do think that there'll come a point where a lot
of these financial institutions will turn around and say, well, if we can't beat them, we'll join
them. Otherwise they will be put under significant pressure. Longer term, do you guys want to be one
flagship product, more akin to a circle, or do you want to be a suite of products or somewhere in the
middle when it comes to how many tokens and on-chain offerings you have? I think we're
organically finding that out ourselves. I mean, we initially wanted to start as this retail on
and off ramp that was integrated with open banking and automated KYC and AML to make this seamless
interoperability between Be It and Pounds on Chain. And I guess as we've sort of developed
as individuals and as an organization, we've seen that change between client demand and also
our own ideas. I think yield products on chain make a lot of sense. And I guess we've kind of
seen that with what Circle's doing with their acquisition of Passional. I think for us, we will
have quite a narrow suite of products. We would rather have quality over quantity. I think there's
a requirement for stablecoin issuers to not just be an issuer and to be a really good quality
infrastructure provider as well. Because at the end of the day, if you want organizations to
integrate and build on top of your product, you need to make it particularly easy and attractive
for them to do that work. I wanted to ask you one final question, which is what is the user
behavior change you're seeing at the moment that makes you compelled that this is going to happen
or what makes you excited that you're seeing in the market? I think for us, it's the level of
willingness of high level individuals in organizations that we would probably consider
as not really being particularly forward thinking or innovative, being willing and open to have
these conversations, looking to move at a pace that we would consider to be quite fast for them.
And the level of ideation that they have themselves. I think it's very easy for us to say
that a lot of financial institutions and also large corporates are quite behind the curve,
but I actually don't think they are. I think a lot of them are thinking about this. And so that
gives us a lot of motivation, particularly in the level of inbound that we're also receiving. I don't
feel like we've got a huge uphill battle on finding good quality distribution partners.
They're out there and it's up to us to deliver a commercial situation that works well for both
parties. It's good to hear people are listening. It's been a pleasure having you on. Thanks for
joining us. Thanks for having me. Thanks for listening to another episode of On the Brink
with Castle Island. To find out more about Castle Island, visit castleisland.vc. To listen to all of
our podcast episodes, please go to onthebrink-podcast.com or just click on the tab in our website. Thanks for
listening.